Guide to the John B. Andrews Papers TAM.113
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John B. Andrews Papers
1864-1908
1906-1908
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Andrews, John B. (John Bertram), 1880-1943
Stein, Leon
TAM.113
1.10 Linear Feet in a record carton and 8 folders in a shared manuscript box
John B. Andrews (1880-1943) was a labor historian, secretary of the American Association for Labor Legislation (1905-1942), and author. The John B. Andrews Papers (dated 1864-1908) contain notes that were used to write "Volumes IX: Labor Movement, 1860-1880, Volume 1" and "Volumes X: Labor Movement, 1860-1880, Volume 2," which are chapters in the book A Documentary History of American Industrial Society. Materials in the collection consist of research notecards, a Ph.D. exam, newspaper articles, outlines, and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Leon Stein at an unknown date. The accession number associated with this gift is 1984.012.
Biographical Note
John B. Andrews (1880-1943) was a labor historian, secretary of the American Association for Labor Legislation (1905-1942), and author. He studied at the University of Wisconson (B.A. 1904). He founded and edited the American Labor Legislation Review; authored A Documentary History of American Industrial Society, Vol. IX and X (1910-1911); Principles of Legislation (1916); History of Labor in the United States (1918); and numerous government reports.
Custodial History
Leon Stein sent a gift of John B. Andrew's research notes. The accession number associated with this gift is 1984.012. Leon Stein obtained the materials from Nelson Frank.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library: Manuscript Files (TAM 245) contains several Andrews manuscripts, including ""International Assembly of North America, 1864," "The Attitude of Organized Labor Toward the Land Question, 1863-1873," his M.A. thesis on Employers' Associations, and his PhD dissertation.
Scope and Contents
The materials found in this collection were used to write "Volumes IX: Labor Movement, 1860-1880, Volume 1" and "Volumes X: Labor Movement, 1860-1880, Volume 2," which are chapters in the book A Documentary History of American Industrial Society. Most of the notes were compiled from labor newspapers, interviews with former union members, and secondary sources. They reflect the organizing efforts and concerns of the early unions. Other materials include a Ph.D. exam given to Andrews and Helen Sumner (1908); newspaper articles; outlines; and correspondence.
The research note cards housed in Box 1 cover the following topics:
American Bureau of Industrial Research: Contains biographical notes written by Andrews on his academic background, description of research methods, and impressions received during the year.
Biography and Research References: Brief notes taken on secondary sources and citation references.
Cities, Summer 1906: Notations on principal cities visited by Andrews. They include Chicago, Detroit, Cleveland, Buffalo, Rochester, Utica, Albany, Worcester, Boston, New York, Philadelphia, Washington D.C., and Pittsburgh.
Labor Journals: Includes general notes on labor journals located, the majority of which are filed by title. A separate section in this series indexes the the Daily Evening, News, (Boston 1864-1866), with cards filed by subject. It also includes an index to Fincher's Trade Review.
Labor Research Notes: Brief notes taken from secondary sources on the labor movement from 1820 to 1880.
Labor Subjects -- this makes up the majority of the note cards. Subjects are arranged alphabetically and include 50 subjects. They are: Anarchism, Arbitration, Boycott, Builders, Carpenters, Charity, Child Labor, Cigarmakers, City Central, Class Struggle, Communism, Contracts, Cooperation, Domestic Labor, Eugenics, Employers' Associations, Factories, Farmers, Hours, Immigration, Imprisonment for Debt, Industrial Evolution, I.W.A., Justice, Knights of labor, Knights of St. Crispin, Land, Labor Movement, Legal, Legislation, Machinists, Mechanics, Mail Order Business, Money, National Labor Union, Protection, Printers, Public Authority, Public Employment, Reminiscenses, Riots, Settlements, Socialism, Strikes, Sunday Work, Suffrage, Wages, Trades Unions, Value, and Woman's Work. The subject Woman's Work was made into a separate series because of its size.
Woman's Work: Shows the extent of organizing activities prior to 1900 undertaken by the Knights of Labor in those professions dominated by women.
Additional paper materials including a Ph.D. exam, newspaper articles, outlines, and correspondence are housed in Box Shared Tamiment 200.
Labor laws and legislation -- United States.; Research notes.; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor -- United States -- Periodicals.; Newspaper columns.; Correspondence.; Commons, John Rogers, 1862-1945; Ely, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1854-1943; Knights of Labor; Stein, Leon
- Research Index Cards (Box 1)
- P.h.D. Exam -- Andrews and Sumner, 1908 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 8)
- Financial Statement for A.B.I.R., 1907-1908 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 9)
- Newspaper articles from Woman's Work Series, 1905-1907 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 10)
- From Labor Subject Series, Politics, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 11)
- Newspaper Articles, Mail Order Business, 1907-1908 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 12)
- Newspaper article on Employers' Associations, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 13)
- Notes for Biography, 1864-1868 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 14)
- Notes on Wages, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 15)
- Notes on "Mrs. Rodgers," Union Organizer, 1886 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 16)
- Notes on Letterhead written in London, 1910 (Box Shared Tamiment 200, Folder 17)